<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<opml version="2.0">
  <head>
    <title>Interaction of a vortex ring with the free surface of ideal fluid</title>
    <dateModified></dateModified>
    <ownerName>V.P. Ruban [^1]\
[*Optics and Fluid Dynamics Department,*]{}\
[*Risø National Laboratory, DK-4000 Roskilde Denmark*]{}

[^1]: Permanent address: L.D.Landau Institute for Theoretical Physics, 2
    Kosygin str., 117334 Moscow, Russia.    E-mail: ruban@itp.ac.ru</ownerName>
  </head>
  <body>
<outline text="Introduction" _note="The study of interaction between vortex structures in a fluid and the&#10;free surface is important both from practical and theoretical points of&#10;view. In general, a detailed investigation of this problem is very hard.&#10;Even the theories of potential surface waves and the dynamics of&#10;vortices in an infinite space taken separately still have a lot of&#10;unsolved fundamental problems on their own. Only the consideration of&#10;significantly simplified models can help us to understand the processes&#10;which take place in the combined system.&#10;&#10;In many cases it is possible to neglect the compressibility of the fluid&#10;as well as the energy dissipation. Therefore the model of ideal&#10;homogeneous incompressible fluid is very useful for hydrodynamics.&#10;Because of the conservative nature of this model the application of the&#10;well developed apparatus of Hamiltonian dynamics becomes possible&#10;[@Arnold] [@ZK97]. An example of effective use of the Hamiltonian&#10;formalism in hydrodynamics is the introduction of canonical variables&#10;for investigations of potential flows of perfect fluids with a free&#10;boundary. V.E.Zakharov showed at the end of the sixties [@Z68] that the&#10;surface shape and the value of the velocity potential on the surface can&#10;be considered as generalized coordinate and momentum, respectively.&#10;&#10;It is important to note that a variational formulation of Hamiltonian&#10;dynamics in many cases allows to obtain good finite-dimensional&#10;approximations which reflect the main features of the behavior of the&#10;original system. There are several possibilities for a parameterization&#10;of non-potential flows of perfect fluid by some variables with dynamics&#10;determined by a variational principle. All of them are based on the&#10;conservation of the topological characteristics of vortex lines in ideal&#10;fluid flows which follows from the freezing-in of the vorticity field .&#10;In particular, this is the representation of the vorticity by Clebsch&#10;canonical variables and [@Lamb] [@ZK97] However, the Clebsch&#10;representation can only describe flows with a trivial topology (see,&#10;e.g., [@KM80]). It cannot describe flows with linked vortex lines.&#10;Besides, the variables and are not suitable for the study of localized&#10;vortex structures like vortex filaments. In such cases it is more&#10;convenient to use the parameterization of vorticity in terms of vortex&#10;lines and consider the motion of these lines [@Berdichevsky],[@KR98],&#10;even if the global definition of canonically conjugated variables is&#10;impossible due to topological reasons.&#10;&#10;This approach is used in the present article to describe the interaction&#10;of deep (or small) vortex rings of almost ideal shape in the perfect&#10;fluid with the free surface. In the case under consideration the main&#10;interaction of the vortex rings with the surface can be described as the&#10;dipole-dipole interaction between “point” vortex rings and their&#10;“images”. Moving rings interact with the surface waves, leading to&#10;radiation due to the Cherenkov effect. Deep rings disturb the surface&#10;weakly, so the influence of the surface can be taken into account as&#10;some small corrections in the equations of motion for the parameters of&#10;the rings.&#10;&#10;In Sec.2 we discuss briefly general properties of vortex line dynamics,&#10;which follow from the freezing-in of the vorticity field. In Sec.3&#10;possible simplifications of the model are made and the point ring&#10;approximation is introduced. In Sec.4 the interaction of the ring with&#10;its image is considered. In Sec.5 we calculate the Fourier-components of&#10;Cherenkov surface waves radiated by a moving vortex ring and determine&#10;the non-conservative corrections caused by the interaction with the&#10;surface for the vortex ring equations of motion.">
</outline>
<outline text="Vortex lines motion in perfect fluid" _note="It is a well known fact that the freezing-in of the vorticity lines&#10;follows from the Euler equation for ideal fluid motion Vortex lines are&#10;transported by the flow [@Arnold],[@Lamb],[@LL6]. They do not appear or&#10;disappear, neither they intersect one another in the process of motion.&#10;This property of perfect fluid flows is general for all Hamiltonian&#10;systems of the hydrodynamic type. For simplicity, let us consider&#10;temporally the incompressible fluid without free surface in infinite&#10;space. The dynamics of the system is specified by a basic Lagrangian ,&#10;which is a functional of the solenoidal velocity field. The relations&#10;between the velocity , the generalized vorticity , the basic Lagrangian&#10;and the Hamiltonian are the following [@R99][^1] and the equation of&#10;motion for the generalized vorticity is This equation corresponds to the&#10;transport of frozen-in vortex lines by the velocity field. In this&#10;process all topological invariants [@MonSas] of the vorticity field are&#10;conserved. The conservation of the topology can be expressed by the&#10;following relation [@KR98] where the mapping describes the deformation&#10;of lines of some initial solenoidal field . Here is the inverse mapping&#10;with respect to . The direction of the vector coincides with the&#10;direction of the vorticity field at the point . The equation of motion&#10;for the mapping can be obtained with the help of the relation which&#10;immediately follows from Eq.(\[OmegaR\]). The substitution of&#10;Eq.(\[OmegaRt\]) into the equation of motion (\[Ham\]) gives [@KR_PRE99]&#10;One can solve this equation by eliminating the operator. Using the&#10;general relationship between variational derivatives of some functional&#10;it is possible to represent the equation of motion for as follows It is&#10;not difficult to check now that the dynamics of the vorticity field with&#10;topological properties defined by in the infinite space is equivalent to&#10;the requirement of an extremum of the action () where the Lagrangian is&#10;[@KR98]&#10;&#10;In the simplest case, when all vortex lines are closed it is possible to&#10;choose new curvilinear coordinates in -space such that Eq.(\[OmegaR\])&#10;can be written in a simple form Here is the label of a line lying on a&#10;fixed two-dimensional manifold , and is some parameter along the line.&#10;It is clear that there is a gauge freedom in the definition of and .&#10;This freedom is connected with the possibility of changing the&#10;longitudinal parameter and also with the relabeling of&#10;&#10;Now we again consider the ordinary perfect fluid with a free surface. To&#10;describe the flow entirely it is sufficient to specify the vorticity&#10;field and the motion of the free surface. Thus, we can use the shape of&#10;the vortex lines as a new dynamic object instead of . It is important to&#10;note that in the presence of the free surface the equations of motion&#10;for follow from a variational principle as in the case of infinite&#10;space. It has been shown [@KR99] that the Lagrangian for a perfect&#10;fluid, with vortices in its bulk and with a free surface, can be written&#10;in the form The functions and are the surface degrees of freedom for the&#10;system. is the boundary value of total velocity potential, which&#10;includes the part from vortices inside the fluid, and is the deviation&#10;of the surface from the horizontal plane. This formulation supposes that&#10;vortex lines do not intersect the surface anywhere. In the present paper&#10;only this case is considered.&#10;&#10;The Hamiltonian in Eq.(\[Lagr1\]) is nothing else than the total energy&#10;of the system expressed in terms of .&#10;&#10;Variation with respect to of the action defined by the Lagrangian&#10;(\[Lagr1\]) gives the equation of motion for vortex lines in the form&#10;This equation determines only the transversal component of which&#10;coincides with the transversal component of the actual solenoidal&#10;velocity field. The possibility of solving Eq.(\[transv\]) with respect&#10;to the time derivative is closely connected with the special gauge&#10;invariant nature of the dependence which results in&#10;&#10;The tangential component of with respect to vorticity direction can be&#10;taken arbitrary. This property is in accordance with the longitudinal&#10;gauge freedom. The vorticity dynamics does not depend on the choice of&#10;the tangential component.&#10;&#10;Generally speaking, only the local introduction of canonical variables&#10;for curve dynamics is possible. For instance, a piece of the curve can&#10;be parameterized by one of the three of Cartesian coordinates In this&#10;case the functions and are canonically conjugated variables. Another&#10;example is the parameterization in cylindrical coordinates, where&#10;variables and are canonically conjugated.&#10;&#10;Curves with complicated topological properties need a general gauge free&#10;description by means of a parameter .&#10;&#10;It should be mentioned for clarity that the conservation of all vortex&#10;tube volumes, reflecting the incompressibility of the fluid, is not the&#10;constraint in this formalism. It is a consequence of the symmetry of the&#10;Lagrangian (\[Lagr1\]) with respect to the relabeling (\[nu\_relabl\])&#10;[@R99]. Volume conservation follows from that symmetry in accordance&#10;with Noether’s theorem. To prove this statement, we should consider such&#10;subset of relabelings which forms a one-parameter group of&#10;transformations of the dynamical variables. For small values of the&#10;group parameter, , the transformations are determined by a function of&#10;two variables (with zero value on the boundary ) so that Due to&#10;Noether’s theorem, the following quantity is an integral of motion&#10;[@DNF] After simple integrations in parts the last expression takes the&#10;form where is the volume of an infinitely thin vortex tube with&#10;cross-section . It is obvious that actually the function doesn’t depend&#10;on time because the function is arbitrary [^2].&#10;&#10;[^1]: For the ordinary ideal hydrodynamics in infinite space the basic&#10;    Lagrangian is The Hamiltonian in this case coincides with the&#10;    kinetic energy of the fluid and in terms of the vorticity field it&#10;    reads where is the inverse Laplace operator.&#10;&#10;    Another example is the basic Lagrangian of Electron&#10;    Magneto-hydrodynamics which takes into account the magnetic field&#10;    created by the current of electron fluid through the motionless ion&#10;    fluid.&#10;&#10;    The second example shows that the relation between the velocity and&#10;    the vorticity can be more complex than in usual hydrodynamics.&#10;&#10;[^2]: If vortex lines are not closed but form a family of enclosed tori&#10;    then the relabeling freedom is less rich. In that case one can&#10;    obtain by the similar way the conservation laws for volumes inside&#10;    closed vortex surfaces. Noether’s theorem gives integrals of motion&#10;    which depend on an arbitrary function of one variable , where is the&#10;    label of the tori.">
</outline>
<outline text="Point ring approximation" _note="In general case an analysis of the dynamics defined by the Lagrangian&#10;(\[Lagr1\]) is too much complicated. We do not even have the exact&#10;expression for the Hamiltonian because it needs the explicit knowledge&#10;of the solution of the Laplace equation with a boundary value assigned&#10;on a non-flat surface. Another reason is the very high nonlinearity of&#10;the problem.&#10;&#10;In this paper we consider some limits where it is possible to simplify&#10;the system significantly. Namely, we will suppose that the vorticity is&#10;concentrated in several very thin vortex rings of almost ideal shape.&#10;For a solitary ring the perfect shape is stable for a wide range of&#10;vorticity distributions through the cross-section. This shape provides&#10;an extremum of the energy for given values of the volumes of vortex&#10;tubes and for a fixed momentum of the ring. As already mentioned, volume&#10;conservation follows from Noether’s theorem. Therefore some of these&#10;quantities (those of which are produced by the subset of commuting&#10;transformations) can be considered as canonical momenta. Corresponding&#10;cyclical coordinates describe the relabeling (\[nu\_relabl\]) of the&#10;line markers, which doesn’t change the vorticity field. Actually these&#10;degrees of freedom take into account a rotation around the central line&#10;of the tube. This line represents the mean shape of the ring and we are&#10;interested in how it behaves in time. For our analysis we don’t need the&#10;explicit values of cyclical coordinates, but only the conserved volumes&#10;as parameters in the Lagrangian.&#10;&#10;A possible situation is when a typical time of the interaction with the&#10;surface and with other rings is much larger then the largest period of&#10;oscillations corresponding to deviations of the ring shape from perfect&#10;one. Under this condition, excitations of all (non-cyclical) internal&#10;degrees of freedom are small during all the time, and a variational&#10;anzats completely disregarding them reflects the behavior of the system&#10;adequately. The circulations of the velocity for each ring don’t depend&#10;on time. A perfect ring is described by the coordinate of the center and&#10;by the vector , where is an oriented area of the ring. We use in this&#10;work the Cartesian system of coordinates , so that the vertical&#10;coordinate is , and the unperturbed surface is at . The corresponding&#10;components of the vectors and are It is easy to verify that the vectors&#10;are canonically conjugated momenta for the coordinates . To verify that&#10;we can parameterize the shape of each vortex line in the following&#10;manner Here are complex vectors. Substituting this into the first term&#10;of the Lagrangian (\[Lagr1\]) gives If we neglect the internal degrees&#10;of freedom which describe deviations of the ring from the ideal shape&#10;then the previous statement about canonically conjugated variables&#10;becomes obvious: Such an approximation is valid only in the limit when&#10;sizes of rings are small in comparison with the distances to the surface&#10;and the distances between different rings These conditions are necessary&#10;for ensuring that the excitations of all internal degrees of freedom are&#10;small. Obviously, this is not true when a ring approaches the surface.&#10;In that case one should take into account also the internal degrees of&#10;freedom for the vortex lines.&#10;&#10;The inequalities (\[dipoles\]) also imply that vortex rings in the limit&#10;under consideration are similar to point magnet dipoles. This analogy is&#10;useful for calculation of the Hamiltonian for interacting rings. In the&#10;main approximation we may restrict the analysis by taking into account&#10;the dipole-dipole interaction only.&#10;&#10;It should be mentioned that in some papers (see e.g. [@Chorin] and&#10;references in that book) the discrete variables identical to and are&#10;derived in a different way and referred as the vortex magnetization&#10;variables.&#10;&#10;In the expression for the Hamiltonian, several simplifications can be&#10;made. Let us recall that for each moment of time it is possible to&#10;decompose the velocity field into two components Here the field&#10;satisfies the following conditions The boundary value of the surface&#10;wave potential is . In accordance with these conditions the kinetic&#10;energy is decomposed into two parts and the Hamiltonian of the fluid&#10;takes the form The last term in this expression is the potential energy&#10;of the fluid in the gravitational field. If all vortex rings are far&#10;away from the surface then its deviation from the horizontal plane is&#10;small Therefore in the main approximation the energy of dipoles&#10;interaction with the surface can be described with the help of so called&#10;“images”. The images are vortex rings with parameters&#10;&#10;The kinetic energy for the system of point rings and their images is the&#10;sum of the self-energies of rings and the dipole-dipole interaction&#10;between them. The expression for the kinetic energy of small amplitude&#10;surface waves employs the operator which multiplies Fourier-components&#10;of a function by the absolute value of a two-dimensional wave vector .&#10;So the real Hamiltonian is approximately equal to the simplified&#10;Hamiltonian&#10;&#10;With the logarithmic accuracy the self-energy of a thin vortex ring is&#10;given by the expression where the small constant is proportional to the&#10;conserved volume of the vortex tube forming the ring. This expression&#10;can easily be derived if we take into account that the main contribution&#10;to the energy is from the vicinity of the tube where the velocity field&#10;is approximately the same as near a straight vortex tube. The&#10;logarithmic integral should then be taken between the limits from the&#10;thickness of the tube to the radius of the ring.&#10;&#10;In the relation the potential is approximately equal to the potential&#10;created on the flat surface by the dipoles and their images&#10;&#10;In this way we arrive at the following simplified system describing the&#10;interaction of point vortex rings with the free surface&#10;&#10;It should be noted that due to the condition (\[dipoles\]) the maximum&#10;value of the velocity on the surface is much less then the typical&#10;velocities of the vortex rings Therefore the term in the Bernoulli&#10;equation is small in comparison with the term . The Lagrangian&#10;(\[tildeL\]) is in accordance with this fact because it does not take&#10;into account terms like in the Hamiltonian expansion.">
</outline>
<outline text="Interaction of the vortex ring with its image" _note="Now let us for simplicity consider the case of a single ring. It is&#10;shown in the next section, that for a sufficiently deep ring the&#10;interaction with its image is much stronger than the interaction with&#10;the surface waves. So it is interesting to examine the motion of the&#10;ring neglecting the surface deviation. In this case we have the&#10;integrable Hamiltonian for the system with two degrees of freedom where&#10;. The system has integrals of motion so it is useful to consider the&#10;level lines of the energy function in the left -half-plane taking as the&#10;parameter (see the Figure).&#10;&#10;\[E\_levels\]&#10;&#10;One can distinguish three regions of qualitatively different behavior of&#10;the ring in that part of this half-plane where our approximation is&#10;valid (see Eq.(\[dipoles\])). In the upper region the phase trajectories&#10;come from infinitely large negative where they have a finite positive&#10;value of . In the process of motion increases. This behavior corresponds&#10;to the case when the ring approaches the surface. Due to the symmetry of&#10;the Hamiltonian (\[2df\]) there is a symmetric lower region, where the&#10;vortex ring moves away from the surface. And there is the middle region,&#10;where changes the sign from negative to positive at a finite value of .&#10;This is the region of the finite motion.&#10;&#10;In all three cases the track of the vortex ring bends toward the&#10;surface, i.e. the ring is “attracted” by the surface.">
</outline>
<outline text="Cherenkov interaction of a vortex ring with surface waves" _note="When the ring is not very far from the surface and not very slow, the&#10;interaction with the surface waves becomes significant. Let us consider&#10;the effect of Cherenkov radiation of surface waves by a vortex ring&#10;which moves from the infinity to the surface. This case is the most&#10;definite from the viewpoint of initial conditions choice. We suppose&#10;that the deviation of the free surface from the horizontal plane is zero&#10;at , and we are interested in the asymptotic behavior of fields and at&#10;large negative . In this situation we can neglect the interaction of the&#10;ring with its image in comparison with the self-energy and concentrate&#10;our attention on interaction with surface waves only.&#10;&#10;The ring moves in the -plane with an almost constant velocity. In the&#10;main approximation the position of the vortex ring is given by the&#10;relations The equations of motion for the Fourier-components of and&#10;follow from the Lagrangian (\[tildeL\]) Eliminating we obtain an&#10;equation for where is the Fourier-transform of the function . Simple&#10;calculations give where Finally, we have for Due to the exponential time&#10;behavior of it is easy to obtain the expressions for and . Introducing&#10;the definition we can represent the answer in the following form&#10;&#10;The radiated surface waves influence the motion of the vortex ring. The&#10;terms produced by the field in the equations of motion for the ring come&#10;from the part in the Lagrangian (\[tildeL\]). Using Eq.(\[Phi\_k\]) for&#10;the Fourier-transform of we can represent these terms as follows We can&#10;use Eq.(\[eta\_kt\]) to obtain the nonconservative corrections for time&#10;derivatives of the ring parameters from these expressions. It is&#10;convenient to write down these corrections in the autonomic form where&#10;and can be understood as explicit functions of defined by the dependence&#10;. More exact definition of and as and is not necessary.&#10;&#10;To analyze the above integrals let us first perform there the&#10;integration over the angle in -space. It is convenient to use the theory&#10;of contour integrals in the complex plane of variable . The contour of&#10;integration in our case goes clockwise just around the cut which is from&#10;to . We define the sign of the square root so that its values are&#10;positive on the top side of the cut and negative on the bottom side.&#10;After introducing the quantities we have to use the following relations&#10;&#10; where the sign of the complex square root should be taken in accordance&#10;with the previous choice. It can easily be seen that the integrals and&#10;have resonance structure at and . This is the Cherenkov effect itself.&#10;Now the expressions (\[dX\]-\[dPz\]) take the form Here the functions&#10;are defined by the integrals and is a dimensionless quantity [^1]. The&#10;Cherenkov effect is most clear when the motion of the ring is almost&#10;horizontal. In this case , and it is convenient to rewrite these&#10;integrals without use of complex functions Here the square root is the&#10;usual positive defined real function. We see that only resonant&#10;wave-numbers contribute to the functions and , while and are determined&#10;also by small values of which correspond to the large scale surface&#10;deviation co-moving with the ring. So the effect of the Cherenkov&#10;radiation on the vortex ring motion is the most distinct in the&#10;equations for and . Especially it is important for because the radiation&#10;of surface waves is the only reason for change of this quantity in the&#10;frame of our approximation.&#10;&#10;The typical values of are large in practical situations. In this limit&#10;asymptotic values of the integrals above are and It follows from these&#10;expressions that the interaction with the surface waves is small in&#10;comparison with the interaction between ring and its image, if . The&#10;corresponding small factors are for and , and for . As against the flat&#10;boundary, now is not conserved. It decreases exponentially slowly and&#10;this is the main effect of Cherenkov radiation.&#10;&#10;We see also that the interaction with waves turns the vector towards the&#10;surface which results in a more fast boundary approach by the ring&#10;track.&#10;&#10;[^1]: If we consider a fluid with surface tension , then two parameters&#10;    appear: and . In that case one should substitute as the second&#10;    argument of the functions in the integrals (\[F1\]-\[G2\])">
</outline>
<outline text="Conclusions and acknowledgments" _note="In this paper we have derived the simplified Lagrangian for the&#10;description of the motion of deep vortex rings under free surface of&#10;perfect fluid. We have analyzed the integrable dynamics corresponding to&#10;the pure interaction of the single point vortex ring with its image. It&#10;was found that there are three types of qualitatively different&#10;behaviour of the ring. The interaction of the ring with the surface has&#10;an attractive character in all three regimes. The Fourier-components of&#10;radiated Cherenkov waves were calculated for the case when the vortex&#10;ring comes from infinity and has both horizontal and vertical components&#10;of the velocity. The non-conservative corrections to the equations of&#10;motion of the ring, due to Cherenkov radiation, were derived. Due to&#10;these corrections the track of the ring bends towards the surface faster&#10;then in the case of flat surface. For simplicity, all calculations in&#10;Sec.5 were performed for a single ring. The generalization for the case&#10;of many rings is straightforward.&#10;&#10;The author thanks professor J.J. Rasmussen for his attention to this&#10;work and for helpful suggestions. This work was supported by the INTAS&#10;(grant No. 96-0413), the Russian Foundation for Basic Research (grant&#10;No. 97-01-00093), and the Landau Postdoc Scholarship (KFA,&#10;Forschungszentrum, Juelich, Germany).&#10;&#10;[99]{}&#10;&#10;V. I. Arnol’d, [*Mathematical Methods of Classical Mechanics*]{}, 2nd&#10;edition (Springer-Verlag, New York, 1989) \[Russian original, Nauka,&#10;Moscow, 1974\].&#10;&#10;V.E.Zakharov and E.A.Kuznetsov, Usp.Fiz.Nauk [**167**]{}, 1037 (1997).&#10;&#10;V.E.Zakharov, Prikl. Mekh. Tekh. Fiz., No.2, 86 (1968).&#10;&#10;H. Lamb, [*Hydrodynamics*]{}, 6th edition (Cambridge University Press,&#10;Cambridge, 1932) \[Russian translation, Gostekhizdat, Moscow, 1947\].&#10;&#10;E.A.Kuznetsov and A.V.Mikhailov, Phys. Lett. A [**77**]{}, 37 (1980).&#10;&#10;V.Berdichevsky, Phys. Rev. E, [**57**]{}, 2885 (1998).&#10;&#10;E.A.Kuznetsov and V.P.Ruban, Pis’ma v ZhETF, [**67**]{}, 1012, (1998)&#10;\[JETP Letters, [**67**]{}, 1076, (1998)\].&#10;&#10;L. D. Landau and E. M. Lifshitz, [*Fluid Mechanics*]{} (Pergamon Press,&#10;New York) \[Russian original, Nauka, Moscow, 1988\].&#10;&#10;V.P.Ruban, ZhETF, [**116**]{}, 563–585 (1999). \[JETP, [**89**]{}, 299,&#10;(1999)\].&#10;&#10;M. I. Monastyrskii and P. V. Sasorov, Zh. Eksp. Teor. Fiz. [**93**]{},&#10;1210 (1987) \[Sov. Phys. JETP [**66**]{}, 683 (1987)\].&#10;&#10;E.A.Kuznetsov and V.P.Ruban, [*Phys. Rev. E*]{}, [**61**]{}, N.1, 831&#10;(2000).&#10;&#10;E.A.Kuznetsov and V.P.Ruban, ZhETF, [**115**]{}, 894-919, (1999).&#10;\[JETP, [**88**]{}, 492, (1999)\].&#10;&#10;B.A.Dubrovin, S.P.Novikov, and A.T.Fomenko, [*Modern Geometry*]{}&#10;(Nauka, Moscow, 1979).&#10;&#10;A.J.Chorin, [*Vorticity and Turbulence*]{}, Springer-Verlag, New York,&#10;1994.">
</outline>
  </body>
</opml>
