<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<opml version="2.0">
  <head>
    <title>Interaction of a vortex ring with the free surface of ideal fluid</title>
    <dateModified></dateModified>
    <ownerName>V.P. Ruban [^1]\
[*Optics and Fluid Dynamics Department,*]{}\
[*Risø National Laboratory, DK-4000 Roskilde Denmark*]{}

[^1]: Permanent address: L.D.Landau Institute for Theoretical Physics, 2
    Kosygin str., 117334 Moscow, Russia.    E-mail: ruban@itp.ac.ru</ownerName>
  </head>
  <body>
<outline text="Introduction" _note="The study of interaction between vortex structures in a fluid and the&#10;free surface is important both from practical and theoretical points of&#10;view. In general, a detailed investigation of this problem is very hard.&#10;Even the theories of potential surface waves and the dynamics of&#10;vortices in an infinite space taken separately still have a lot of&#10;unsolved fundamental problems on their own. Only the consideration of&#10;significantly simplified models can help us to understand the processes&#10;which take place in the combined system.&#10;&#10;In many cases it is possible to neglect the compressibility of the fluid&#10;as well as the energy dissipation. Therefore the model of ideal&#10;homogeneous incompressible fluid is very useful for hydrodynamics.&#10;Because of the conservative nature of this model the application of the&#10;well developed apparatus of Hamiltonian dynamics becomes possible&#10;[@Arnold] [@ZK97]. An example of effective use of the Hamiltonian&#10;formalism in hydrodynamics is the introduction of canonical variables&#10;for investigations of potential flows of perfect fluids with a free&#10;boundary. V.E.Zakharov showed at the end of the sixties [@Z68] that the&#10;surface shape $z=\eta(x,y,t)$ and the value of the velocity potential&#10;$\psi(x,y,t)$ on the surface can be considered as generalized coordinate&#10;and momentum, respectively.&#10;&#10;It is important to note that a variational formulation of Hamiltonian&#10;dynamics in many cases allows to obtain good finite-dimensional&#10;approximations which reflect the main features of the behavior of the&#10;original system. There are several possibilities for a parameterization&#10;of non-potential flows of perfect fluid by some variables with dynamics&#10;determined by a variational principle. All of them are based on the&#10;conservation of the topological characteristics of vortex lines in ideal&#10;fluid flows which follows from the freezing-in of the vorticity field&#10;${\bf \Omega }({\bf r},t)=\mbox{curl}\,{\bf v}({\bf r},t)$. In&#10;particular, this is the representation of the vorticity by Clebsch&#10;canonical variables $\lambda$ and $\mu$ [@Lamb] [@ZK97]&#10;$${\bf \Omega }({\bf r},t)=[\nabla\lambda\times\nabla\mu]$$ However, the&#10;Clebsch representation can only describe flows with a trivial topology&#10;(see, e.g., [@KM80]). It cannot describe flows with linked vortex lines.&#10;Besides, the variables $\lambda$ and $\mu$ are not suitable for the&#10;study of localized vortex structures like vortex filaments. In such&#10;cases it is more convenient to use the parameterization of vorticity in&#10;terms of vortex lines and consider the motion of these lines&#10;[@Berdichevsky],[@KR98], even if the global definition of canonically&#10;conjugated variables is impossible due to topological reasons.&#10;&#10;This approach is used in the present article to describe the interaction&#10;of deep (or small) vortex rings of almost ideal shape in the perfect&#10;fluid with the free surface. In the case under consideration the main&#10;interaction of the vortex rings with the surface can be described as the&#10;dipole-dipole interaction between “point” vortex rings and their&#10;“images”. Moving rings interact with the surface waves, leading to&#10;radiation due to the Cherenkov effect. Deep rings disturb the surface&#10;weakly, so the influence of the surface can be taken into account as&#10;some small corrections in the equations of motion for the parameters of&#10;the rings.&#10;&#10;In Sec.2 we discuss briefly general properties of vortex line dynamics,&#10;which follow from the freezing-in of the vorticity field. In Sec.3&#10;possible simplifications of the model are made and the point ring&#10;approximation is introduced. In Sec.4 the interaction of the ring with&#10;its image is considered. In Sec.5 we calculate the Fourier-components of&#10;Cherenkov surface waves radiated by a moving vortex ring and determine&#10;the non-conservative corrections caused by the interaction with the&#10;surface for the vortex ring equations of motion.">
</outline>
<outline text="Vortex lines motion in perfect fluid" _note="It is a well known fact that the freezing-in of the vorticity lines&#10;follows from the Euler equation for ideal fluid motion&#10;$${\bf\Omega}_t=\mbox{curl}\,[{\bf v}\times{\bf\Omega}], \qquad&#10;{\bf v}=\mbox{curl}^{-1}\,{\bf\Omega }$$ Vortex lines are transported by&#10;the flow [@Arnold],[@Lamb],[@LL6]. They do not appear or disappear,&#10;neither they intersect one another in the process of motion. This&#10;property of perfect fluid flows is general for all Hamiltonian systems&#10;of the hydrodynamic type. For simplicity, let us consider temporally the&#10;incompressible fluid without free surface in infinite space. The&#10;dynamics of the system is specified by a basic Lagrangian $L[{\bf v}]$,&#10;which is a functional of the solenoidal velocity field. The relations&#10;between the velocity ${\bf v}$, the generalized vorticity ${\bf\Omega}$,&#10;the basic Lagrangian $L[{\bf v}]$ and the Hamiltonian&#10;${\cal H}[{\bf\Omega}]$ are the following [@R99][^1]&#10;$${\bf\Omega}=\mbox{curl}\left(\frac{\delta L}{\delta{\bf v}}\right)\qquad&#10;\Rightarrow \qquad {\bf v}={\bf v}[{\bf\Omega}]$$&#10;$${\cal H}[{\bf\Omega}]=&#10;\left(\int{\bf v}\cdot\left(\frac{\delta{ L}}{\delta{\bf v}}\right)d^3{\bf r}&#10;-{L}[{\bf v}]\right)\Big|_{{\bf v}={\bf v}[{\bf\Omega}]}$$&#10;$${\bf v}=\mbox{curl}\left(\frac{\delta{\cal H}}{\delta{\bf\Omega}}\right)$$&#10;and the equation of motion for the generalized vorticity is&#10;$$\label{Ham}&#10;{\bf\Omega}_t=\mbox{curl}\,&#10;[\mbox{curl}\,(\delta{\cal H}/\delta{\bf\Omega})\times{\bf\Omega}]$$&#10;This equation corresponds to the transport of frozen-in vortex lines by&#10;the velocity field. In this process all topological invariants [@MonSas]&#10;of the vorticity field are conserved. The conservation of the topology&#10;can be expressed by the following relation [@KR98] $$\label{OmegaR}&#10;{\bf \Omega }({\bf r},t)=\int \delta({\bf r}-{\bf R}({\bf a},t))&#10;({\bf \Omega}_{0}({\bf a})\nabla _{{\bf a}}){\bf R}({\bf a},t)d{\bf a}=&#10;\frac{({\bf \Omega}_{0}({\bf a})\nabla _{{\bf a}}){\bf R}({\bf a},t)}&#10;{\mbox{det}\|\partial{\bf R}/\partial{\bf a}\|}&#10;\Big|_{{\bf a}={\bf a}({\bf r},t)}$$ where the mapping&#10;${\bf R}({\bf a},t)$ describes the deformation of lines of some initial&#10;solenoidal field ${\bf \Omega}_{0}({\bf r})$. Here ${\bf a}({\bf r},t)$&#10;is the inverse mapping with respect to ${\bf R}({\bf a},t)$. The&#10;direction of the vector ${\bf b}$ $$\label{b}&#10;{\bf b}({\bf a},t)=&#10;({\bf \Omega}_{0}({\bf a})\nabla _{{\bf a}}){\bf R}({\bf a},t)$$&#10;coincides with the direction of the vorticity field at the point&#10;${\bf R}({\bf a},t)$. The equation of motion for the mapping&#10;${\bf R}({\bf a},t)$ can be obtained with the help of the relation&#10;$$\label{OmegaRt}&#10;{\bf\Omega}_t({\bf r},t)=&#10;\mbox{curl}_{\bf r}\int&#10;\delta({\bf r}-{\bf R}({\bf a},t))&#10;[{\bf R}_t({\bf a},t)\times{\bf b}({\bf a},t)]&#10;d{\bf a},$$ which immediately follows from Eq.(\[OmegaR\]). The&#10;substitution of Eq.(\[OmegaRt\]) into the equation of motion (\[Ham\])&#10;gives [@KR_PRE99]&#10;$$\mbox{curl}_{\bf r}\left(\frac{{\bf b}({\bf a},t)\times&#10;[{\bf R}_t({\bf a},t)-{\bf v}({\bf R},t)]}&#10;{\mbox{det}\|\partial{\bf R}/\partial{\bf a}\|}\right)=0$$ One can solve&#10;this equation by eliminating the $\mbox{curl}_{\bf r}$ operator. Using&#10;the general relationship between variational derivatives of some&#10;functional $F[{\bf \Omega }]$ $$\label{peresch}&#10;\left[ {\bf b}\times \mbox{curl}\left( \frac{\delta F}{\delta {\bf \Omega }&#10;({\bf R})}\right) \right] =\frac{\delta F}{\delta {\bf R}({\bf a})}&#10;\Big|_{{\bf \Omega }_{0}}$$ it is possible to represent the equation of&#10;motion for ${\bf R}({\bf a},t)$ as follows&#10;$$\left[ ({\bf \Omega }_{0}({\bf a})\nabla _{{\bf a}}){\bf R}({\bf a})\times&#10;{\bf R}_{t}({\bf a})\right] =&#10;\frac{\delta {\cal H}[{\bf \Omega }[{\bf R}]]}&#10;{\delta {\bf R}({\bf a})}\Big|_{{\bf \Omega }_{0}}.  \label{main}$$ It&#10;is not difficult to check now that the dynamics of the vorticity field&#10;with topological properties defined by ${\bf \Omega}_{0}$ in the&#10;infinite space is equivalent to the requirement of an extremum of the&#10;action ($\delta S=\delta\int {\cal L}_{{\bf \Omega}_{0}}dt=0$) where the&#10;Lagrangian is [@KR98] $${\cal L}_{{\bf \Omega}_{0}}=&#10;\frac{1}{3}\int\Big(\left[ {\bf R}_{t}({\bf a})\times&#10;{\bf R}({\bf a})\right]\cdot({\bf \Omega }_{0}({\bf a})\nabla _{{\bf a}})&#10;{\bf R}({\bf a})\Big)d{\bf a} &#10; - {\cal H}[{\bf \Omega }[{\bf R}]].  \label{LAGRANGIAN}$$&#10;&#10;In the simplest case, when all vortex lines are closed it is possible to&#10;choose new curvilinear coordinates $\nu_1,\nu_2,\xi$ in ${\bf a}$-space&#10;such that Eq.(\[OmegaR\]) can be written in a simple form&#10;$$\label{lines}&#10;{\bf \Omega }({\bf r},t)=\int_{\cal N}d^2\nu \oint \delta ({\bf r}-&#10;{\bf R}(\nu,\xi,t)){\bf R}_{\xi}d\xi.$$ Here $\nu$ is the label of a&#10;line lying on a fixed two-dimensional manifold ${\cal N}$, and $\xi$ is&#10;some parameter along the line. It is clear that there is a gauge freedom&#10;in the definition of $\nu$ and $\xi$. This freedom is connected with the&#10;possibility of changing the longitudinal parameter&#10;$\xi=\xi(\tilde\xi,\nu,t)$ and also with the relabeling of $\nu$&#10;$$\label{nu_relabl}&#10;\nu=\nu(\tilde\nu,t),\qquad&#10;\frac{\partial(\nu_1,\nu_2)}&#10;{\partial(\tilde\nu_1,\tilde\nu_2)}=1.$$&#10;&#10;Now we again consider the ordinary perfect fluid with a free surface. To&#10;describe the flow entirely it is sufficient to specify the vorticity&#10;field ${\bf \Omega }({\bf r},t)$ and the motion of the free surface.&#10;Thus, we can use the shape ${\bf R}(\nu,\xi,t)$ of the vortex lines as a&#10;new dynamic object instead of ${\bf \Omega }({\bf r},t)$. It is&#10;important to note that in the presence of the free surface the equations&#10;of motion for ${\bf R}(\nu,\xi,t)$ follow from a variational principle&#10;as in the case of infinite space. It has been shown [@KR99] that the&#10;Lagrangian for a perfect fluid, with vortices in its bulk and with a&#10;free surface, can be written in the form $$\label{Lagr1}&#10;{\cal L}=\frac{1}{3} \int_{\cal N} d^2\nu &#10;\oint([{\bf R}_t\times{\bf R}]\cdot{\bf R}_{\xi})d\xi+&#10;\int \Psi \eta_t d{\bf r}_{\bot} -{\cal H}[{\bf R},\Psi,\eta].$$ The&#10;functions $\Psi({\bf r}_{\bot},t)$ and $\eta({\bf r}_{\bot},t)$ are the&#10;surface degrees of freedom for the system. $\Psi$ is the boundary value&#10;of total velocity potential, which includes the part from vortices&#10;inside the fluid, and $\eta$ is the deviation of the surface from the&#10;horizontal plane. This formulation supposes that vortex lines do not&#10;intersect the surface anywhere. In the present paper only this case is&#10;considered.&#10;&#10;The Hamiltonian ${\cal H}$ in Eq.(\[Lagr1\]) is nothing else than the&#10;total energy of the system expressed in terms of $[{\bf R},\Psi,\eta]$.&#10;&#10;Variation with respect to ${\bf R}(\nu,\xi,t)$ of the action defined by&#10;the Lagrangian (\[Lagr1\]) gives the equation of motion for vortex lines&#10;in the form $$\label{transv}&#10;[{\bf R}_\xi\times{\bf R}_t]=\frac{\delta{\cal H}[{\bf\Omega[R]},\Psi,\eta]}&#10;{\delta{\bf R}} \; .$$ This equation determines only the transversal&#10;component of ${\bf R}_t$ which coincides with the transversal component&#10;of the actual solenoidal velocity field. The possibility of solving&#10;Eq.(\[transv\]) with respect to the time derivative ${\bf R}_t$ is&#10;closely connected with the special gauge invariant nature of the&#10;${\cal H}[{\bf R}]$ dependence which results in $$\frac{\delta{\cal H}}&#10;{\delta{\bf R}}\cdot {\bf R}_\xi \equiv 0 \; .$$&#10;&#10;The tangential component of ${\bf R}_t$ with respect to vorticity&#10;direction can be taken arbitrary. This property is in accordance with&#10;the longitudinal gauge freedom. The vorticity dynamics does not depend&#10;on the choice of the tangential component.&#10;&#10;Generally speaking, only the local introduction of canonical variables&#10;for curve dynamics is possible. For instance, a piece of the curve can&#10;be parameterized by one of the three of Cartesian coordinates&#10;$${\bf R}=(X(z,t),Y(z,t),z)$$ In this case the functions $X(z,t)$ and&#10;$Y(z,t)$ are canonically conjugated variables. Another example is the&#10;parameterization in cylindrical coordinates, where variables&#10;$Z(\theta,t)$ and $(1/2)R^2(\theta,t)$ are canonically conjugated.&#10;&#10;Curves with complicated topological properties need a general gauge free&#10;description by means of a parameter $\xi$.&#10;&#10;It should be mentioned for clarity that the conservation of all vortex&#10;tube volumes, reflecting the incompressibility of the fluid, is not the&#10;constraint in this formalism. It is a consequence of the symmetry of the&#10;Lagrangian (\[Lagr1\]) with respect to the relabeling (\[nu\_relabl\])&#10;$\nu\to\tilde\nu$ [@R99]. Volume conservation follows from that symmetry&#10;in accordance with Noether’s theorem. To prove this statement, we should&#10;consider such subset of relabelings which forms a one-parameter group of&#10;transformations of the dynamical variables. For small values of the&#10;group parameter, $\tau$, the transformations are determined by a&#10;function of two variables $T(\nu_1,\nu_2)$ (with zero value on the&#10;boundary $\partial {\cal N}$) so that $$\label{transf}&#10;{\bf R}(\nu_1,\nu_2,\xi)\to{\bf R}^\tau_T(\nu_1,\nu_2,\xi)=&#10;{\bf R}\Bigg(\nu_1-\tau\frac{\partial T}{\partial \nu_2}+O(\tau^2),\,\,\,&#10;\nu_2+\tau\frac{\partial T}{\partial \nu_1}+O(\tau^2),\,\,\,\xi\Bigg)$$&#10;Due to Noether’s theorem, the following quantity is an integral of&#10;motion [@DNF] $$I_T=\int_{\cal N} d^2\nu\oint&#10;\frac{\delta{\cal L}}{\delta {\bf R}_t}\cdot&#10;\frac{\partial{\bf R}^\tau_T}{\partial\tau}\Bigg|_{\tau=0} \!\!d\xi&#10;=\frac{1}{3} \int_{\cal N} d^2\nu &#10;\oint[{\bf R}\times{\bf R}_\xi]\cdot({\bf R}_2 T_1-{\bf R}_1 T_2)d\xi$$&#10;After simple integrations in parts the last expression takes the form&#10;$$I_T= \int_{\cal N} d^2\nu \oint T(\nu_1,\nu_2)&#10;([{\bf R}_1\times{\bf R}_2]\cdot{\bf R}_\xi)d\xi=&#10;\int_{\cal N}  T(\nu_1,\nu_2){\cal V}(\nu_1,\nu_2,t)d^2\nu$$ where&#10;${\cal V}(\nu_1,\nu_2,t)d^2\nu$ is the volume of an infinitely thin&#10;vortex tube with cross-section $d^2\nu$. It is obvious that actually the&#10;function ${\cal V}$ doesn’t depend on time $t$ because the function&#10;$T(\nu_1,\nu_2)$ is arbitrary [^2].&#10;&#10;[^1]: For the ordinary ideal hydrodynamics in infinite space the basic&#10;    Lagrangian is&#10;    $$L_{Euler}[{\bf v}]=\int \frac{{\bf v}^2}{2}d{\bf r}\qquad &#10;    \Rightarrow \qquad {\bf\Omega}=\mbox{curl}\,{\bf v}$$ The&#10;    Hamiltonian in this case coincides with the kinetic energy of the&#10;    fluid and in terms of the vorticity field it&#10;    reads$${\cal H}_{Euler}[{\bf\Omega}]=&#10;    -1/2\int {\bf\Omega}\Delta^{-1}{\bf\Omega}\,d{\bf r}=&#10;    \frac{1}{8\pi}\int\!\!\int&#10;    \frac{{\bf\Omega}({\bf r}_1)\cdot{\bf\Omega}({\bf r}_2)}&#10;    {|{\bf r}_1-{\bf r}_2|}d{\bf r}_1d{\bf r}_2$$ where $\Delta^{-1}$ is&#10;    the inverse Laplace operator.&#10;&#10;    Another example is the basic Lagrangian of Electron&#10;    Magneto-hydrodynamics which takes into account the magnetic field&#10;    created by the current of electron fluid through the motionless ion&#10;    fluid.&#10;    $$L_{EMHD}[{\bf v}]=\frac{1}{2}\int{\bf v}(1-\Delta^{-1}){\bf v}\,d{\bf r}\qquad &#10;    \Rightarrow \qquad {\bf\Omega}=\mbox{curl}(1-\Delta^{-1}){\bf v}$$&#10;    $${\cal H}_{EMHD}[{\bf\Omega}]=\frac{1}{2}\int &#10;    {\bf\Omega}(1-\Delta)^{-1}{\bf\Omega}\,d{\bf r}=&#10;    \frac{1}{8\pi}\int\!\!\int&#10;    \frac{e^{-|{\bf r}_1-{\bf r}_2|}}{|{\bf r}_1-{\bf r}_2|}&#10;    {\bf\Omega}({\bf r}_1)\cdot{\bf\Omega}({\bf r}_2)d{\bf r}_1d{\bf r}_2$$&#10;&#10;    The second example shows that the relation between the velocity and&#10;    the vorticity can be more complex than in usual hydrodynamics.&#10;&#10;[^2]: If vortex lines are not closed but form a family of enclosed tori&#10;    then the relabeling freedom is less rich. In that case one can&#10;    obtain by the similar way the conservation laws for volumes inside&#10;    closed vortex surfaces. Noether’s theorem gives integrals of motion&#10;    which depend on an arbitrary function of one variable $S(\zeta)$,&#10;    where $\zeta$ is the label of the tori.">
</outline>
<outline text="Point ring approximation" _note="In general case an analysis of the dynamics defined by the Lagrangian&#10;(\[Lagr1\]) is too much complicated. We do not even have the exact&#10;expression for the Hamiltonian ${\cal H}[{\bf R},\Psi,\eta]$ because it&#10;needs the explicit knowledge of the solution of the Laplace equation&#10;with a boundary value assigned on a non-flat surface. Another reason is&#10;the very high nonlinearity of the problem.&#10;&#10;In this paper we consider some limits where it is possible to simplify&#10;the system significantly. Namely, we will suppose that the vorticity is&#10;concentrated in several very thin vortex rings of almost ideal shape.&#10;For a solitary ring the perfect shape is stable for a wide range of&#10;vorticity distributions through the cross-section. This shape provides&#10;an extremum of the energy for given values of the volumes of vortex&#10;tubes and for a fixed momentum of the ring. As already mentioned, volume&#10;conservation follows from Noether’s theorem. Therefore some of these&#10;quantities (those of which are produced by the subset of commuting&#10;transformations) can be considered as canonical momenta. Corresponding&#10;cyclical coordinates describe the relabeling (\[nu\_relabl\]) of the&#10;line markers, which doesn’t change the vorticity field. Actually these&#10;degrees of freedom take into account a rotation around the central line&#10;of the tube. This line represents the mean shape of the ring and we are&#10;interested in how it behaves in time. For our analysis we don’t need the&#10;explicit values of cyclical coordinates, but only the conserved volumes&#10;as parameters in the Lagrangian.&#10;&#10;A possible situation is when a typical time of the interaction with the&#10;surface and with other rings is much larger then the largest period of&#10;oscillations corresponding to deviations of the ring shape from perfect&#10;one. Under this condition, excitations of all (non-cyclical) internal&#10;degrees of freedom are small during all the time, and a variational&#10;anzats completely disregarding them reflects the behavior of the system&#10;adequately. The circulations $$\Gamma_n=\int_{{\cal N}_n}d^2\nu$$ of the&#10;velocity for each ring don’t depend on time. A perfect ring is described&#10;by the coordinate ${\bf R}_n$ of the center and by the vector&#10;${\bf P}_n=\Gamma_n{\bf S}_n$, where ${\bf S}_n$ is an oriented area of&#10;the ring. We use in this work the Cartesian system of coordinates&#10;$(x,y,z)$, so that the vertical coordinate is $z$, and the unperturbed&#10;surface is at $z=0$. The corresponding components of the vectors&#10;${\bf R}_n$ and ${\bf P}_n$ are&#10;$${\bf R}_n=(X_n,Y_n,Z_n),\qquad {\bf P}_n=(P_{xn},P_{yn},P_{zn})$$ It&#10;is easy to verify that the vectors ${\bf P}_n$ are canonically&#10;conjugated momenta for the coordinates ${\bf R}_n$. To verify that we&#10;can parameterize the shape of each vortex line in the following manner&#10;$${\bf R}(\xi,t)=\sum_{m=-M}^{M}{\bf r}_m(t)e^{im\xi},&#10;\qquad {\bf r}_{-m}=\bar{\bf r}_m$$ Here ${\bf r}_m(t)$ are complex&#10;vectors. Substituting this into the first term of the Lagrangian&#10;(\[Lagr1\]) gives&#10;$$\frac{1}{3}\oint([{\bf R}_t\times{\bf R}]{\bf R}_{\xi})d\xi=&#10;2\pi i\dot{\bf r}_0([{\bf r}_{-1}\times{\bf r}_1]+&#10;2[{\bf r}_{-2}\times{\bf r}_2]+\dots)+$$&#10;$$+\frac{d \{...\}}{dt}+2\pi i\dot{\bf r}_{-1}[{\bf r}_{-1}\times{\bf r}_2]&#10;-2\pi i\dot{\bf r}_1[{\bf r}_1\times{\bf r}_{-2}] +\dots$$ If we neglect&#10;the internal degrees of freedom which describe deviations of the ring&#10;from the ideal shape $$({\bf r}_{-1})^2=({\bf r}_1)^2=0 ,\qquad&#10;{\bf r}_2={\bf r}_{-2}=0,\qquad\dots$$ then the previous statement about&#10;canonically conjugated variables becomes obvious:&#10;$${\bf R}_n={\bf r}_{0n},\qquad&#10;{\bf P}_n=2\pi \Gamma_n \cdot i[{\bf r}_{-1n}\times{\bf r}_{1n}]$$ Such&#10;an approximation is valid only in the limit when sizes of rings are&#10;small in comparison with the distances to the surface and the distances&#10;between different rings $$\label{dipoles}&#10;\sqrt{\frac{P_n}{\Gamma_n}}\ll |Z_n|,|{\bf R}_{n}-{\bf R}_{l}|,&#10;\qquad l\not=n.$$ These conditions are necessary for ensuring that the&#10;excitations of all internal degrees of freedom are small. Obviously,&#10;this is not true when a ring approaches the surface. In that case one&#10;should take into account also the internal degrees of freedom for the&#10;vortex lines.&#10;&#10;The inequalities (\[dipoles\]) also imply that vortex rings in the limit&#10;under consideration are similar to point magnet dipoles. This analogy is&#10;useful for calculation of the Hamiltonian for interacting rings. In the&#10;main approximation we may restrict the analysis by taking into account&#10;the dipole-dipole interaction only.&#10;&#10;It should be mentioned that in some papers (see e.g. [@Chorin] and&#10;references in that book) the discrete variables identical to&#10;${\bf R}_{n}$ and ${\bf P}_n$ are derived in a different way and&#10;referred as the vortex magnetization variables.&#10;&#10;In the expression for the Hamiltonian, several simplifications can be&#10;made. Let us recall that for each moment of time it is possible to&#10;decompose the velocity field into two components&#10;$${\bf v}={\bf V}_0+\nabla\phi.$$ Here the field ${\bf V}_0$ satisfies&#10;the following conditions&#10;$$(\nabla\cdot{\bf V}_0)=0,\qquad \mbox{curl}{\bf V}_0={\bf \Omega},\qquad&#10;({\bf n}\cdot{\bf V}_0)|_{z=\eta}=0.$$ The boundary value of the surface&#10;wave potential $\phi({\bf r})$ is $\psi({\bf r}_\bot)$. In accordance&#10;with these conditions the kinetic energy is decomposed into two parts&#10;and the Hamiltonian of the fluid takes the form&#10;$${\cal H}=\frac{1}{2}\int_{z&lt;\eta}{\bf V}_0^2d^3{\bf r}+&#10;\frac{1}{2}\int\psi(\nabla\phi\cdot d{\bf S})+&#10;\frac{g}{2}\int\eta^2d{\bf r}_{\bot}$$ The last term in this expression&#10;is the potential energy of the fluid in the gravitational field. If all&#10;vortex rings are far away from the surface then its deviation from the&#10;horizontal plane is small $$\label{smallangle}&#10;|\nabla\eta|\ll 1,\qquad|\eta|\ll|Z_n|$$ Therefore in the main&#10;approximation the energy of dipoles interaction with the surface can be&#10;described with the help of so called “images”. The images are vortex&#10;rings with parameters $$\Gamma_n,\qquad&#10;{\bf R}^*_n=(X_n,Y_n,-Z_n),\qquad {\bf P}^*_n=(P_{xn},P_{yn},-P_{zn})$$&#10;&#10;The kinetic energy for the system of point rings and their images is the&#10;sum of the self-energies of rings and the dipole-dipole interaction&#10;between them. The expression for the kinetic energy of small amplitude&#10;surface waves employs the operator $\hat k$ which multiplies&#10;Fourier-components of a function by the absolute value $k$ of a&#10;two-dimensional wave vector ${\bf k}$. So the real Hamiltonian&#10;${\cal H}$ is approximately equal to the simplified Hamiltonian&#10;$\tilde{\cal H}$ $${\cal H}\approx\tilde{\cal H}=&#10;\frac{1}{2}\int(\psi\hat k \psi+g\eta^2)d{\bf r}_{\bot}&#10;+\sum_n {\cal E}_n(P_n)+$$ $$+\frac{1}{8\pi}\sum_{l\not= n}&#10;\frac{3(({\bf R}_n-{\bf R}_l)\cdot{\bf P}_n)&#10;(({\bf R}_n-{\bf R}_l)\cdot{\bf P}_l)-&#10;|{\bf R}_n-{\bf R}_l|^2({\bf P}_n\cdot{\bf P}_l)}&#10;{|{\bf R}_n-{\bf R}_l|^5}+\quad$$ $$+\frac{1}{8\pi}\sum_{l n}&#10;\frac{3(({\bf R}_n-{\bf R}^*_l)\cdot{\bf P}_n)&#10;(({\bf R}_n-{\bf R}^*_l)\cdot{\bf P}^*_l)-&#10;|{\bf R}_n-{\bf R}^*_l|^2({\bf P}_n\cdot{\bf P}^*_l)}&#10;{|{\bf R}_n-{\bf R}^*_l|^5}$$&#10;&#10;With the logarithmic accuracy the self-energy of a thin vortex ring is&#10;given by the expression $${\cal E}_n(P_n)\approx\frac{\Gamma_n^2}{2}&#10;\sqrt{\frac{P_n}{\pi\Gamma_n}}&#10;\ln\left(\frac{(P_n/\Gamma_n)^{3/4}}{A_n^{1/2}}\right)$$ where the small&#10;constant $A_n$ is proportional to the conserved volume of the vortex&#10;tube forming the ring. This expression can easily be derived if we take&#10;into account that the main contribution to the energy is from the&#10;vicinity of the tube where the velocity field is approximately the same&#10;as near a straight vortex tube. The logarithmic integral should then be&#10;taken between the limits from the thickness of the tube to the radius of&#10;the ring.&#10;&#10;In the relation $\Psi=\Phi_0+\psi$ the potential $\Phi_0$ is&#10;approximately equal to the potential created on the flat surface by the&#10;dipoles and their images&#10;$$\Phi_0({\bf r}_\bot)\approx\Phi({\bf r}_\bot)=&#10;-\frac{1}{2\pi}\sum_n&#10;\frac{({\bf P}_n\cdot({\bf r}_\bot-{\bf R}_n))}&#10;{|{\bf r}_\bot-{\bf R}_n|^3}$$&#10;&#10;In this way we arrive at the following simplified system describing the&#10;interaction of point vortex rings with the free surface $$\label{tildeL}&#10;\tilde{\cal L}=\sum_n \dot{\bf R}_n{\bf P}_n+&#10;\int \dot\eta(\psi+\Phi)d^2{\bf r}_\bot-&#10;\tilde{\cal H}[\{{\bf R}_n,{\bf P}_n\},\eta,\psi]$$&#10;&#10;It should be noted that due to the condition (\[dipoles\]) the maximum&#10;value of the velocity $V_0$ on the surface is much less then the typical&#10;velocities of the vortex rings&#10;$$\frac{P_n}{Z_n^3}\ll\frac{\Gamma_n^{3/2}}{P_n^{1/2}}$$ Therefore the&#10;term $V_0^2/2$ in the Bernoulli equation&#10;$$\Psi_t +V_0^2/2 +g\eta +\mbox{small corrections}=0$$ is small in&#10;comparison with the term $\Psi_t$. The Lagrangian (\[tildeL\]) is in&#10;accordance with this fact because it does not take into account terms&#10;like $(1/2)\int V_0^2\eta d^2{\bf r}_\bot$ in the Hamiltonian expansion.">
</outline>
<outline text="Interaction of the vortex ring with its image" _note="Now let us for simplicity consider the case of a single ring. It is&#10;shown in the next section, that for a sufficiently deep ring the&#10;interaction with its image is much stronger than the interaction with&#10;the surface waves. So it is interesting to examine the motion of the&#10;ring neglecting the surface deviation. In this case we have the&#10;integrable Hamiltonian for the system with two degrees of freedom&#10;$$\label{2df}&#10;H=\frac{1}{64\pi}\left(&#10;\alpha(P_x^2+P_z^2)^{1/4} -\frac{2P_z^2+P_x^2}{|Z|^3}\right),&#10;\qquad Z&lt;0$$ where $\alpha\approx \mbox{const}$. The system has&#10;integrals of motion $$P_x=p=const, \qquad H=E=const$$ so it is useful to&#10;consider the level lines of the energy function in the left&#10;$(Z,P_z)$-half-plane taking $P_x$ as the parameter (see the Figure).&#10;&#10;\[E\_levels\]&#10;&#10;One can distinguish three regions of qualitatively different behavior of&#10;the ring in that part of this half-plane where our approximation is&#10;valid (see Eq.(\[dipoles\])). In the upper region the phase trajectories&#10;come from infinitely large negative $Z$ where they have a finite&#10;positive value of $P_z$. In the process of motion $P_z$ increases. This&#10;behavior corresponds to the case when the ring approaches the surface.&#10;Due to the symmetry of the Hamiltonian (\[2df\]) there is a symmetric&#10;lower region, where the vortex ring moves away from the surface. And&#10;there is the middle region, where $P_z$ changes the sign from negative&#10;to positive at a finite value of $Z$. This is the region of the finite&#10;motion.&#10;&#10;In all three cases the track of the vortex ring bends toward the&#10;surface, i.e. the ring is “attracted” by the surface.">
</outline>
<outline text="Cherenkov interaction of a vortex ring with surface waves" _note="When the ring is not very far from the surface and not very slow, the&#10;interaction with the surface waves becomes significant. Let us consider&#10;the effect of Cherenkov radiation of surface waves by a vortex ring&#10;which moves from the infinity to the surface. This case is the most&#10;definite from the viewpoint of initial conditions choice. We suppose&#10;that the deviation of the free surface from the horizontal plane $z=0$&#10;is zero at $t\to-\infty$, and we are interested in the asymptotic&#10;behavior of fields $\eta$ and $\psi$ at large negative $t$. In this&#10;situation we can neglect the interaction of the ring with its image in&#10;comparison with the self-energy and concentrate our attention on&#10;interaction with surface waves only.&#10;&#10;The ring moves in the $(x,z)$-plane with an almost constant velocity. In&#10;the main approximation the position ${\bf R}$ of the vortex ring is&#10;given by the relations $${\bf R}\approx{\bf C}t,\qquad &#10;{\bf C}={\bf C}({\bf P})=&#10;\frac{\partial{\cal E}}{\partial{\bf P}}=(C_x,0,C_z)\sim\frac{\bf P}{P^{3/2}},$$&#10;$$\qquad C_x&gt;0,\qquad C_z&gt;0,\qquad t&lt;0.$$ The equations of motion for&#10;the Fourier-components of $\eta$ and $\psi$ follow from the Lagrangian&#10;(\[tildeL\]) $$\dot\eta_{\bf k}=k\psi_{\bf k},\qquad&#10;\dot\psi_{\bf k}+g\eta_{\bf k}=-\dot\Phi_{\bf k}$$ Eliminating&#10;$\eta_{\bf k}$ we obtain an equation for $\psi_{\bf k}$&#10;$$\ddot\psi_{\bf k}+gk\psi_{\bf k}=-\ddot\Phi_{\bf k}$$ where&#10;$\Phi_{\bf k}$ is the Fourier-transform of the function&#10;$\Phi({\bf r}_\bot)$. Simple calculations give&#10;$$\Phi_{\bf k}=\frac{e^{-ik_x X}}{2\pi}\int&#10;\frac{P_z Z-P_x x}{\sqrt{(x^2+y^2+Z^2)^3}}&#10;e^{-i(k_x x+k_y y)}dx\,dy=$$ $$=-\frac{e^{-ik_x X}}{2\pi}&#10;\left(P_zD(k|Z|)+i\frac{P_x}{|Z|}\frac{\partial}{\partial k_x}D(k|Z|)&#10;\right)$$ where $$D(q)=\int\frac{e^{-iq\alpha}d\alpha\,d\beta}&#10;{\sqrt{(\alpha^2+\beta^2+1)^3}}=2\pi e^{-|q|}$$ Finally, we have for&#10;$\Phi_{\bf k}$ $$\label{Phi_k}&#10;\Phi_{\bf k}=\left(\frac{iP_xk_x}{k}-P_z\right)e^{-k|Z|-ik_xX}=&#10;\left(\frac{iP_xk_x}{k}-P_z\right)e^{t(kC_z-ik_xC_x)}$$ Due to the&#10;exponential time behavior of $\Phi_{\bf k}(t)$ it is easy to obtain the&#10;expressions for $\psi_{\bf k}(t)$ and $\eta_{\bf k}(t)$. Introducing the&#10;definition $$\lambda_{\bf k}=kC_z-ik_xC_x$$ we can represent the answer&#10;in the following form&#10;$$\psi_{\bf k}(t)=\frac{-\left(\frac{iP_xk_x}{k}-P_z\right)\lambda_{\bf k}^2}&#10;{gk+\lambda_{\bf k}^2}e^{\lambda_{\bf k}t}&#10;=\left(\frac{P}{Ck}\right)\frac{\lambda_{\bf k}^3}&#10;{gk+\lambda_{\bf k}^2}e^{\lambda_{\bf k}t}$$ $$\label{eta_kt}&#10;\eta_{\bf k}(t)=\left(\frac{P}{C}\right)\frac{\lambda_{\bf k}^2}&#10;{gk+\lambda_{\bf k}^2}e^{\lambda_{\bf k}t}$$&#10;&#10;The radiated surface waves influence the motion of the vortex ring. The&#10;terms produced by the field $\eta_{\bf k}(t)$ in the equations of motion&#10;for the ring come from the part $\int \dot\eta\Phi d^2{\bf r}_\bot$ in&#10;the Lagrangian (\[tildeL\]). Using Eq.(\[Phi\_k\]) for the&#10;Fourier-transform of $\Phi$ we can represent these terms as follows&#10;$$\delta \dot X=\int\frac{d^2{\bf k}}{(2\pi)^2}\dot\eta_{\bf k}&#10;\frac{ik_x}{k}e^{kZ+ik_xX}$$&#10;$$\delta \dot Z=\int\frac{d^2{\bf k}}{(2\pi)^2}\dot\eta_{\bf k}&#10;e^{kZ+ik_xX}$$&#10;$$\delta \dot P_x=-\int\frac{d^2{\bf k}}{(2\pi)^2}\dot\eta_{\bf k}\cdot(ik_x)&#10;\left(P_z+\frac{iP_xk_x}{k}\right)e^{kZ+ik_xX}$$&#10;$$\delta \dot P_z=-\int\frac{d^2{\bf k}}{(2\pi)^2}\dot\eta_{\bf k}\cdot k&#10;\left(P_z+\frac{iP_xk_x}{k}\right)e^{kZ+ik_xX}$$ We can use&#10;Eq.(\[eta\_kt\]) to obtain the nonconservative corrections for time&#10;derivatives of the ring parameters from these expressions. It is&#10;convenient to write down these corrections in the autonomic form&#10;$$\label{dX}&#10;\delta \dot X=\left(\frac{P}{C}\right)\int\frac{d^2{\bf k}}{(2\pi)^2}&#10;\left(\frac{ik_x}{k}\right)&#10;\frac{(kC_z-ik_xC_x)^3}{gk+(kC_z-ik_xC_x)^2}&#10;e^{-2k|Z|}$$ $$\label{dZ}&#10;\delta \dot Z=\left(\frac{P}{C}\right)\int\frac{d^2{\bf k}}{(2\pi)^2}\cdot&#10;\frac{(kC_z-ik_xC_x)^3}{gk+(kC_z-ik_xC_x)^2}&#10;e^{-2k|Z|}$$ $$\label{dPx}&#10;\delta \dot P_x=-\left(\frac{P}{C}\right)^2&#10;\int\frac{d^2{\bf k}}{(2\pi)^2}\left(\frac{ik_x}{k}\right)&#10;\frac{(kC_z-ik_xC_x)^2(C_z^2k^2+C_x^2k_x^2)}{gk+(kC_z-ik_xC_x)^2}e^{-2k|Z|}$$&#10;$$\label{dPz}&#10;\delta \dot P_z=-\left(\frac{P}{C}\right)^2&#10;\int\frac{d^2{\bf k}}{(2\pi)^2}\cdot&#10;\frac{(kC_z-ik_xC_x)^2(C_z^2k^2+C_x^2k_x^2)}{gk+(kC_z-ik_xC_x)^2}e^{-2k|Z|}$$&#10;where $C_x$ and $C_z$ can be understood as explicit functions of&#10;${\bf P}$ defined by the dependence&#10;${\bf C}({\bf P})={\partial{\cal E}}/{\partial{\bf P}}$. More exact&#10;definition of $C_x$ and $C_z$ as $\dot X$ and $\dot Z$ is not necessary.&#10;&#10;To analyze the above integrals let us first perform there the&#10;integration over the angle $\varphi$ in ${\bf k}$-space. It is&#10;convenient to use the theory of contour integrals in the complex plane&#10;of variable $w=\cos\varphi$. The contour $\gamma$ of integration in our&#10;case goes clockwise just around the cut which is from $-1$ to $+1$. We&#10;define the sign of the square root $R(w)=\sqrt{1-w^2}$ so that its&#10;values are positive on the top side of the cut and negative on the&#10;bottom side. After introducing the quantities&#10;$$a=\frac{C_z}{C_x},\qquad \omega_{\bf k}^2=gk,\qquad &#10;b_{\bf k}=\frac{\omega_{\bf k}}{C_x k}=\frac{1}{C_x}\sqrt{\frac{g}{k}}$$&#10;we have to use the following relations&#10;$$I_1(a,b)\equiv -\oint\limits_\gamma\frac{d\,w}{\sqrt{1-w^2}}\cdot&#10;\frac{w(w+ia)^3}{b^2-(w+ia)^2}=\qquad\qquad\qquad\qquad\qquad\qquad\qquad$$&#10;$$=\pi(1+2b^2)+\pi i&#10;\left(\frac{(b-ia)b^2}{\sqrt{1-(b-ia)^2}}-\frac{(b+ia)b^2}{\sqrt{1-(-b-ia)^2}}&#10;\right)$$&#10;&#10;$$I_2(a,b)\equiv i\oint\limits_\gamma\frac{d\,w}{\sqrt{1-w^2}}\cdot&#10;\frac{(w+ia)^3}{b^2-(w+ia)^2}=\qquad\qquad\qquad\qquad\qquad\qquad\qquad$$&#10;$$=\pi\left(2a+\frac{b^2}{\sqrt{1-(b-ia)^2}}+\frac{b^2}{\sqrt{1-(-b-ia)^2}}&#10;\right)$$&#10;&#10;$$J_1(a,b)\equiv i\oint\limits_\gamma\frac{d\,w}{\sqrt{1-w^2}}\cdot&#10;\frac{w(w+ia)^2(w^2+a^2)}{b^2-(w+ia)^2}=&#10;\qquad\qquad\qquad\qquad\qquad\qquad$$ $$=-4\pi ab^2+\pi\left(&#10;\frac{b(b-ia)(a^2+(b-ia)^2)}{\sqrt{1-(b-ia)^2}}+&#10;\frac{b(b+ia)(a^2+(b+ia)^2)}{\sqrt{1-(-b-ia)^2}}&#10;\right)$$&#10;&#10;$$J_2(a,b)\equiv \oint\limits_\gamma\frac{d\,w}{\sqrt{1-w^2}}\cdot&#10;\frac{(w+ia)^2(w^2+a^2)}{b^2-(w+ia)^2}=&#10;\qquad\qquad\qquad\qquad\qquad\qquad\quad$$&#10;$$=-2\pi(a^2+b^2+1/2)-\pi i\left(&#10;\frac{b(a^2+(b-ia)^2)}{\sqrt{1-(b-ia)^2}}-&#10;\frac{b(a^2+(b+ia)^2)}{\sqrt{1-(-b-ia)^2}}&#10;\right)$$ where the sign of the complex square root should be taken in&#10;accordance with the previous choice. It can easily be seen that the&#10;integrals $I_2$ and $J_1$ have resonance structure at $a\ll 1$ and&#10;$|b|&lt;1$. This is the Cherenkov effect itself. Now the expressions&#10;(\[dX\]-\[dPz\]) take the form $$\label{dX2}&#10;\delta \dot X=\frac{P_x}{(2\pi)^2}\int\limits_0^{+\infty}&#10;I_1\left(a,b_{\bf k}\right)k^2e^{-2k|Z|}dk=&#10;\frac{P_x}{(2\pi)^2}\left(\frac{g}{C_x^2}\right)^3 &#10;F_1\left(a,\frac{2g|Z|}{C_x^2}\right)$$ $$\label{dZ2}&#10;\delta \dot Z=\frac{P_x}{(2\pi)^2}\int\limits_0^{+\infty}&#10;I_2\left(a,b_{\bf k}\right)k^2e^{-2k|Z|}dk=&#10;\frac{P_x}{(2\pi)^2}\left(\frac{g}{C_x^2}\right)^3 &#10;F_2\left(a,\frac{2g|Z|}{C_x^2}\right)$$ $$\label{dPx2}&#10;\delta \dot P_x=\frac{P_x^2}{(2\pi)^2}\int\limits_0^{+\infty}&#10;J_1\left(a,b_{\bf k}\right)k^3e^{-2k|Z|}dk=&#10;\frac{P_x^2}{(2\pi)^2}\left(\frac{g}{C_x^2}\right)^4 &#10;G_1\left(a,\frac{2g|Z|}{C_x^2}\right)$$ $$\label{dPz2}&#10;\delta \dot P_z=\frac{P_x^2}{(2\pi)^2}\int\limits_0^{+\infty}&#10;J_2\left(a,b_{\bf k}\right)k^3e^{-2k|Z|}dk=&#10;\frac{P_x^2}{(2\pi)^2}\left(\frac{g}{C_x^2}\right)^4 &#10;G_2\left(a,\frac{2g|Z|}{C_x^2}\right)$$ Here the functions&#10;$F_1(a,Q)..G_2(a,Q)$ are defined by the integrals $$\label{F1}&#10;F_1(a,Q)=\int\limits_0^{+\infty}I_1\left(a,\frac{1}{\sqrt{\xi}}\right)&#10;\exp\left(-Q\xi\right)\xi^2\,d\xi$$ $$\label{F2}&#10;F_2(a,Q)=\int\limits_0^{+\infty}I_2\left(a,\frac{1}{\sqrt{\xi}}\right)&#10;\exp\left(-Q\xi\right)\xi^2\,d\xi$$ $$\label{G1}&#10;G_1(a,Q)=\int\limits_0^{+\infty}J_1\left(a,\frac{1}{\sqrt{\xi}}\right)&#10;\exp\left(-Q\xi\right)\xi^3\,d\xi$$ $$\label{G2}&#10;G_2(a,Q)=\int\limits_0^{+\infty}J_2\left(a,\frac{1}{\sqrt{\xi}}\right)&#10;\exp\left(-Q\xi\right)\xi^3\,d\xi$$ and $Q={2g|Z|}/{C_x^2}$ is a&#10;dimensionless quantity [^1]. The Cherenkov effect is most clear when the&#10;motion of the ring is almost horizontal. In this case $a\to +0$, and it&#10;is convenient to rewrite these integrals without use of complex&#10;functions $$F_1(+0,Q)=\pi\int\limits_0^{+\infty}\left(\xi^2+2\xi\right)&#10;\exp\left(-Q\xi\right)\,d\xi-&#10;2\pi\int\limits_0^{1}\frac{\xi\,d\xi}{\sqrt{1-\xi}}&#10;\exp\left(-Q\xi\right)$$ $$F_2(+0,Q)=G_1(+0,Q)=&#10;-2\pi\int\limits_1^{+\infty}\frac{\xi^{3/2}\,d\xi}{\sqrt{\xi-1}}&#10;\exp\left(-Q\xi\right)$$&#10;$$G_2(+0,Q)=-\pi\int\limits_0^{+\infty}\left(\xi^3+2\xi^2\right)&#10;\exp\left(-Q\xi\right)\,d\xi+&#10;2\pi\int\limits_0^{1}\frac{\xi^2\,d\xi}{\sqrt{1-\xi}}&#10;\exp\left(-Q\xi\right)$$ Here the square root is the usual positive&#10;defined real function. We see that only resonant wave-numbers contribute&#10;to the functions $F_2$ and $G_1$, while $F_1$ and $G_2$ are determined&#10;also by small values of $\xi$ which correspond to the large scale&#10;surface deviation co-moving with the ring. So the effect of the&#10;Cherenkov radiation on the vortex ring motion is the most distinct in&#10;the equations for $\dot Z$ and $\dot P_x$. Especially it is important&#10;for $P_x$ because the radiation of surface waves is the only reason for&#10;change of this quantity in the frame of our approximation.&#10;&#10;The typical values of $Q$ are large in practical situations. In this&#10;limit asymptotic values of the integrals above are&#10;$$F_1(+0,Q)\approx-\frac{9\pi}{2Q^4},\qquad &#10;G_2(+0,Q)\approx\frac{18\pi}{Q^5}$$&#10;$$F_2(+0,Q)=G_1(+0,Q)\approx-2\pi\sqrt{\pi}\cdot\frac{\exp(-Q)}{\sqrt{Q}}$$&#10;and&#10;$$\delta \dot X\approx -\frac{9}{64\pi}\frac{P}{|Z|^3}\cdot\frac{1}{Q},\qquad &#10;\delta \dot Z\approx -\frac{1}{16\sqrt{\pi}}&#10;\frac{P}{|Z|^3}\cdot Q^{2+1/2}\exp(-Q),\qquad$$&#10;$$\delta \dot P_x\approx  -\frac{1}{32\sqrt{\pi}}&#10;\frac{P^2}{|Z|^4}\cdot Q^{3+1/2}\exp(-Q),\qquad &#10;\delta \dot P_z\approx +\frac{9}{32\pi}\frac{P^2}{|Z|^4}\cdot\frac{1}{Q}.$$&#10;It follows from these expressions that the interaction with the surface&#10;waves is small in comparison with the interaction between ring and its&#10;image, if $Q\gg 1$. The corresponding small factors are $1/Q$ for $X$&#10;and $P_z$, and $Q^{2+1/2}\exp(-Q)$ for $Z$. As against the flat&#10;boundary, now $P_x$ is not conserved. It decreases exponentially slowly&#10;and this is the main effect of Cherenkov radiation.&#10;&#10;We see also that the interaction with waves turns the vector ${\bf P}$&#10;towards the surface which results in a more fast boundary approach by&#10;the ring track.&#10;&#10;[^1]: If we consider a fluid with surface tension $\sigma$, then two&#10;    parameters appear: $Q$ and $T={g\sigma}/{C_x^4}$. In that case one&#10;    should substitute $b_{\bf k}\to\sqrt{{1}/{\xi}+T\xi}$ as the second&#10;    argument of the functions $I_1,I_2,J_1,J_2$ in the integrals&#10;    (\[F1\]-\[G2\])">
</outline>
<outline text="Conclusions and acknowledgments" _note="In this paper we have derived the simplified Lagrangian for the&#10;description of the motion of deep vortex rings under free surface of&#10;perfect fluid. We have analyzed the integrable dynamics corresponding to&#10;the pure interaction of the single point vortex ring with its image. It&#10;was found that there are three types of qualitatively different&#10;behaviour of the ring. The interaction of the ring with the surface has&#10;an attractive character in all three regimes. The Fourier-components of&#10;radiated Cherenkov waves were calculated for the case when the vortex&#10;ring comes from infinity and has both horizontal and vertical components&#10;of the velocity. The non-conservative corrections to the equations of&#10;motion of the ring, due to Cherenkov radiation, were derived. Due to&#10;these corrections the track of the ring bends towards the surface faster&#10;then in the case of flat surface. For simplicity, all calculations in&#10;Sec.5 were performed for a single ring. The generalization for the case&#10;of many rings is straightforward.&#10;&#10;The author thanks professor J.J. Rasmussen for his attention to this&#10;work and for helpful suggestions. This work was supported by the INTAS&#10;(grant No. 96-0413), the Russian Foundation for Basic Research (grant&#10;No. 97-01-00093), and the Landau Postdoc Scholarship (KFA,&#10;Forschungszentrum, Juelich, Germany).&#10;&#10;[99]{}&#10;&#10;V. I. Arnol’d, [*Mathematical Methods of Classical Mechanics*]{}, 2nd&#10;edition (Springer-Verlag, New York, 1989) \[Russian original, Nauka,&#10;Moscow, 1974\].&#10;&#10;V.E.Zakharov and E.A.Kuznetsov, Usp.Fiz.Nauk [**167**]{}, 1037 (1997).&#10;&#10;V.E.Zakharov, Prikl. Mekh. Tekh. Fiz., No.2, 86 (1968).&#10;&#10;H. Lamb, [*Hydrodynamics*]{}, 6th edition (Cambridge University Press,&#10;Cambridge, 1932) \[Russian translation, Gostekhizdat, Moscow, 1947\].&#10;&#10;E.A.Kuznetsov and A.V.Mikhailov, Phys. Lett. A [**77**]{}, 37 (1980).&#10;&#10;V.Berdichevsky, Phys. Rev. E, [**57**]{}, 2885 (1998).&#10;&#10;E.A.Kuznetsov and V.P.Ruban, Pis’ma v ZhETF, [**67**]{}, 1012, (1998)&#10;\[JETP Letters, [**67**]{}, 1076, (1998)\].&#10;&#10;L. D. Landau and E. M. Lifshitz, [*Fluid Mechanics*]{} (Pergamon Press,&#10;New York) \[Russian original, Nauka, Moscow, 1988\].&#10;&#10;V.P.Ruban, ZhETF, [**116**]{}, 563–585 (1999). \[JETP, [**89**]{}, 299,&#10;(1999)\].&#10;&#10;M. I. Monastyrskii and P. V. Sasorov, Zh. Eksp. Teor. Fiz. [**93**]{},&#10;1210 (1987) \[Sov. Phys. JETP [**66**]{}, 683 (1987)\].&#10;&#10;E.A.Kuznetsov and V.P.Ruban, [*Phys. Rev. E*]{}, [**61**]{}, N.1, 831&#10;(2000).&#10;&#10;E.A.Kuznetsov and V.P.Ruban, ZhETF, [**115**]{}, 894-919, (1999).&#10;\[JETP, [**88**]{}, 492, (1999)\].&#10;&#10;B.A.Dubrovin, S.P.Novikov, and A.T.Fomenko, [*Modern Geometry*]{}&#10;(Nauka, Moscow, 1979).&#10;&#10;A.J.Chorin, [*Vorticity and Turbulence*]{}, Springer-Verlag, New York,&#10;1994.">
</outline>
  </body>
</opml>
